on to another awakening from the meaning
crisis discord q
a with john verveigh thanks for being
here again john
always my pleasure guys always my
pleasure
so we've got a bunch of people here and
we've already have some questions
queued up so like always if you could
queue up your questions
in the event uh text which is right
above
uh the event hall reporting here in the
discord if you want me to read out your
question
please let me know otherwise i'll assume
you want to read your
own question and uh let's just get right
into it strong yoba question for john
hi john hi strong good to hear from you
yeah it's good to hear your voice as
well um okay so i'm just going to read
this out
the narrative practice hypothesis is
based on the idea that narrative doesn't
come naturally to us
it's something that we have to work at
but if we have to practice narrative
then it is possible that we have been
practicing narrative incorrectly
i recall you saying elsewhere that
something can't be a narrative if it
doesn't have a
have something resembling a complete
ending but have you ruled out the
possibility that there it could be
other ways of construing a narrative
with this in mind
why isn't dear logos a practicing of the
art of narrative
yeah so um so when i would i i i
i understand your question and i think
the intent is a very
good question um i took
narrative to be what uh
had to have sort of the constituent
features that hudo argues are needed in
order to perform its function
um uh so carrick uh you need
you uh you need you need character
um you need
plot um you need flash forward flashback
and you need uh conflict resolution
there has to be a problem
uh a problem that requires you
at least vicariously plugging into the
distributed cognition within the story
in order to uh in order to solve the
problem
and so i took it
that um two things
one thing i argued is that we shouldn't
think
of narrative as intrinsic to us and
you've already
acknowledged that at least as a as a
good supposition
and that there are states in which
people go uh
trans-narrative and
i took that i took hudo
um i'm gonna evoke somebody and i'm
gonna be talking to him soon so
this is not just uh promissory uh strong
i'm gonna actually be talking to
james cars i i took narrative uh
at least the way it's classically
understood uh to be something like
um having a resolution um a deniamon the
climax
and all of that etc and therefore to be
an example of what cars calls a finite
game
uh where i took that some of the things
that are supposed to be happening india
logos
and in related um individual experiences
of self-transcendence as be more
an example of what cars calls an
infinite game um
where you're not seeking resolution in
fact what you're constantly doing
if you're you're constantly sort of
trying to gradually rewrite and evolve
the rules
by which the game is played because the
main purpose of the game
is to continue and deepen the
involvement
in the playing of the game and i took
dialogues to be an example of that so
that's
that's what i was thinking that i'm
interested in hearing your feedback on
it that was
that's why i made the move i made um
obviously i haven't given you any kind
of a priori closure argument i'm just
explaining to you my thinking about why
i i did it the way i did um what do you
think about that how would you like to
do that well it just strikes me that
we talk about resolution right um you
also in your logos talk about getting to
a place where you couldn't get on your
own
right it seems to me that there's a
similarity between the resolution and
getting into
getting into that new place yeah but
it's but it's not complete or it's not
full but
it's like a it's like an ongoing playing
right so
we have this idea of like the narrative
broke because
well at least in part when the final
cause was was split off from the
scientific world view then the
right picture of the narrative became uh
nonsensical in in a sort of a sense so
the question is
how how do we rebuild it and what i see
is rebuilding the narrative yeah that's
interesting
it's it's narrative it's or at least
it's trans narrative right
it's you you're you're with me and
acknowledging it's not traditional or
classical narrative
right because yeah yeah well you you're
pl you're playing with the narrative and
well you can't have a particular
narrative uh presupposed when you're
playing with the narrative definitely
right right right right right right
and the idea it would be more like the
the the old that that that that subgenre
that was always sort of questioned by
people
like you you know the the books that
they don't do them anymore because of
the internet stuff but i don't know if
they still do them or not i shouldn't be
presumptuous
you do i you know you you choose your
own adventure kind of thing where you're
you're yes yeah right so that the the
the line also between the author and the
reader
of the narrative uh is the classic line
that the post-modernist makes so much
about right
is really uh is is undermined
significantly
that's also an important part of the
logos and so
yeah go ahead go ahead go ahead yeah
well i was just going to say that that's
a lot like computer games as well
so i mean that's also the playing with
narrative and so i see dia logos
in that sense also related to the to the
kind of the because you talk about how
gaming
brings about the flow state right yeah
yeah yeah
yeah so yeah so i i was kind of toying
with the idea but
because you talk about um well the
narrative practice hypothesis but then
dear logos is the practice of the
narrative it's like
it just makes perfect sense to me that
way somehow it's
yeah i mean one way of thinking about it
i hadn't thought about it and
if you'll allow me to riff on this a bit
so this is just on the moment
but when i'm doing the work i do on the
philosophy of pedagogy
i talk about a particular pedagogical
style that tries to integrate
argumentation in the socratic sense not
the cartesian sense
argumentation and narrative together and
that would
yeah i think that that that that's very
much what the
logos is doing right
do more about this i i really like this
idea that this is a way of going sort of
trans-narrative
that allows us to you know exact the
the narrative function into something
that is more consonant
uh with our current non-telo
non-teleological world view
i think that's a brilliant insight yeah
well i like this i really like this
okay well i'm sure i'll be telling you a
lot more about it in the coming weeks or
months because this is something that
i'm kind of on my own just you know
trying to puzzle out so
uh expect more okay good but like i said
uh
if the the last piece i said i think
would be
important to integrate in that you know
there's a pedagogical principle that is
now different than the standard
pedagogical principle
um well of narrative yeah
i would say that um the platonic
dialogues are very much pedagogical
right
yes exactly you're aiming for all of
that
so that that's what i see yeah yeah and
people
like so a person to take a look at among
others is drew hyland
because he talks a lot and this is the
new reading that i've been mentioning
uh he talks a lot about paying attention
to the drama
in addition to the argument and drama is
a kind of narrative so i think this is
all
converging very nicely yeah i i
would tend to agree um and also like you
know christopher master
pietro's way of trying to like i was
just listening to your uh
podcast about art uh with andrew sweeney
and like a lot of these issues also
tying in there again as well with with
um
art as well and so i think yeah like all
of these things are
coalescing somehow so what about this
then
straw what about the logos as a
reinvention of narrative given
all the work that uh andrew had yeah i
agree with that
yeah yeah that's good i like that
yeah and then also like you know the
issues that you're having with the
jonathan peugeot and stuff that also
it helps to build a better platform for
communication i think
i i think that's right that's exactly
why i like this that's why i'm excited
about it um it might afford more
fruitful dialogue between theism and
and non-theism as well yes yes very much
so very very much so
i've actually got a lot of thoughts
about that as well i don't know if you
want me to jump in there with that or
wait for another question but uh
yeah like you know you do know that i
i don't respond to everything but you
can tell by what i do
that i read what you have to say and i
take it into account
yeah yeah definitely and yeah so i could
also email it
yeah that's great i'd appreciate that
yeah uh send me that email and i think
i'll copy chris on it like i'll get
looped into it okay okay i'll do that
because narrative is his sort of
narrative and drama are his
chosen forms of art that he think are
that he thinks are really central
to this whole project i i remember um
the way that he spoke about uh i think
it was frankenstein with andrew sweeney
and i was really impressed with this
with his uh literally
literary analysis so yeah i would really
look
i think that's a really great idea yeah
he also did one on both
our town uh to play our town it was just
amazing
yeah i'm not familiar with it but i
heard you him speak about it so i i i
actually might even check that out yeah
okay thank you very much
i'm sorry for the rest of uh you uh i'm
not apologizing in in
to strong uh because i just wanted to
follow that whole dialogue up with
strong because that i think that
this isn't this is a really not only
philosophically important but
practically
or practicably important point so i just
wanted to keep going with this a little
bit
so thank you for your patience everyone
else
thank you very much for answering john
thank you strong
great so so manuel is a question now
john manuel is uh
he he he's in our sangha and he you've
you've
answered some questions of his on uh on
the youtube
streams and he is the one who put
together the the 40 minute video
oh or that we're using for meditation so
so he's been
fantastic emanuel thank you so much it's
a pleasure to meet you
i hope you weren't put off by the fact
that we sort of delayed
answering your question right and i
wanted to get i wanted to
get a situation where i i gave you a
chance to explicate it
which you did and then i tried to
respond to it in a stepwise fashion i
hope you found that helpful
yeah that was uh yeah i still need to
find out the answer right because you
you were putting it in the future but
yeah thanks that was that was great
okay so so my question is when
when we are trying to develop like
rituals and games and whatever to
yeah to have a little bit lower barrier
of entry right like
a more accessible right this is with the
scaling problem of religion
um so i was wondering if you could
like paint the space and all the corners
that we need to cover
in order to have like a whole
set i guess
um so and that's i i'm not going to
totally just put you off again because i
don't want you to get the sense that
that's what i'm going to do with you
um but i i i i mean
i was just actually talking to mark and
brett and we want to
set up we're going to set up a meeting
not this week but next week in which we
start the project of
uh like schematizing that about you know
what are sort of the design principles
at the core are setting up
an ecology of practices and then uh
and then sort of a a a a pedagogy
like a pedagogical program then my hope
from that would be
that once people get a sense of that
then people would get
because human beings tend to do this
what if you give them those first two
things
if you give them design functions and a
pedagogical program
then they start to be they start to get
good at generating
they get a sense of prototypes you know
they get a sort of prototypical sense of
what a practice should look like and
that and that starts to guide them i'd
like to do it this way
explicitly daniel because um any sort of
i
like it's good if rituals emerge to some
significant degree
bottom up right rather than just trying
to top down construct them
so my hope is if we get the
schematization going
the way i've just described and people
start practicing it
then they will get a clear sense of oh
this is what a good practice
looks like and i i don't want to give a
definition for the reasons i just gave
you
so i'm not trying to be quite like i
said we're going to specifically try to
address this very soon
right but my question was a little bit
different though right like oh
i'm sorry maybe i misunderstood you
please please please restate it then
so what i was trying to get at is is
religio has a certain essence right so
yeah what i what i wanted to hear is
like
what would be that essence right like
what
would be like if if you talk to a person
on the street like what would you need
to offer that person
in order to say now
okay sorry sorry i i completely
misunderstood you
although i think what i just said was
useful uh for the discord server
um so for me the the
the the the the the central thing is
what you're offering people
um and you're offering them and these
these two are analytically distinct but
they're in practice they're
conjoined it is you're asking you're
offering people
uh systemic systematic and reliable ways
of
overcoming self-deception and
of enhancing the three
axes of connection that we know like
are generative of increased meaning in
life so that the things that undermine
meaning in life are of course an
undermining of agency that's the
self-deceptive thing
and also people being ignorant about
ways in which
they can enhance the sense of
connectedness to themselves to each
other in the world
that sense of being connect of enhancing
all of these practices bring up the way
in which we are our religion are
connected
they bring them up and and enhance them
you say that to people they don't care
but if you say to them but the point of
that the point of enhancing religio is
that is exactly
the engine that drives enhanced
experience not just thought enhanced
experience enhancement realization
of meaning in life then that's what
grabs people because people
want their lives more meat to be more
meaningful
okay thanks i i think i can work with
that
was that too complex or did you want
something even more elevator pitch
well uh well i'm just
looking for for spaces to explore right
like i'm
i'm trying to engage with this design
idea and i'm
i'm trying to get a map of the territory
so
that's that's why i'm asking so the
the main functions that the two
so like i said i think the main
functions that people generally are
coming
looking to being address they need how
to be made aware
of these functions and like
like i said some reliable ways of
overcoming
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
and then
reliable ways of enhancing
the sense of connectedness the sense of
religio itself
and typically people find those
those two things inherently
intrinsically valuable
they don't say but why would i want to
reduce self-deception they just take
that as
oh that would make my life good when you
say
why would i want to enhance meaning in
life people don't ask that question
they just want enhanced meaning in life
okay thanks for answering the question
thank you i mean i'm always open
also like through every channel to like
if
well you've seen refine a question come
back and i'll try and answer it
um in a more refined fashion
uh yeah i'll definitely do that please
please hey karima you have a question
yes
go ahead hello john
and wisdom pilgrims um
my question's on the understanding of
self
firstly uh some see no difference
between notions of
self soul consciousness person
uh you know the witnessing eye or the
the i am with you know creative agency
but when exploring the self you no doubt
consider the no
self and this is my question
a few days ago i learned of the
padlovata buddhist philosophy
and in case listeners don't know it was
a group of five of the early schools of
buddhism in
india and they had a belief in a self
or person not at all like today's
buddhism of no self which i can never
understand given that most buddhists
believe in reincarnation as did even
socrates
but anyways um will your reinvention of
the self
be using the current buddhist ideas of
no self
or the padgolavada view
of a constant transcendent nature
of self i'm sort of uh
i want to move beyond that um i'm
actually teaching a course
um this year um at the university on
exactly this topic
it's the central topic um the nature of
the self
um and so i'm not i'm not just
i don't want to answer you yet because
i'm specifically setting up a structure
and what i'm going to do is and it's a
fourth year seminar course i'm going to
be working with some of the brightest
students
i've got you know we're reading you know
some of the best anthologies the oxford
handbook
on the self uh evan thompson's uh self
no self anthology
a bunch of other things uh because there
is a and you're already alluding it to
it
there's a lot of equivocation and
confusion around this uh what
even what the term means what what both
of them mean what
how it how it sits with the other other
entities in this family resemblance
like soul and spirit and personality and
character
uh and consciousness many people what
one of my
sort of pet peeves is many people who
pronounce uh
know self that all they do is shift all
the functions to self-consciousness
and then that doesn't really really do
anything it just
shifts around on the metaphysics without
answering anything
uh and other people have made that
criticism that's not my only criticism
so karim what i want to do is i i want
to go through that
and i've talked to omar about this we're
going to do that and then once that
course is done and i've sort of
a chance to really um be a logos test
of the ideas and the arguments then i'm
going to
release that as a a a sequence of
lecture videos
uh uh to to my channel so that i i'm
going
i'm devoting a lot of effort to
answering this question
it's going to be a premier thing i do
it's going to be some of the generated
content
but that's not going to come out to
basically like january of next year
because the course i'm teaching goes
from september to december
gosh well it sounds wonderful
i'm very happy you're doing that and you
know i don't know why
the universe brought this article of the
padka lavada
school to my attention but i had no idea
that you know before
india didn't have so many buddhists that
there was
uh you know a belief in uh
you know very different than what i
think of as buddhist nowadays
yeah many people have said that there's
been a lot of scholastic work
around uh the deeper connections between
vedanta and buddhism there are many
people who are now
arguing for a deep continuity between
them
rather than the sort of traditional
oppositional presentation of buddhism
and aspects of vedanta um and so
yeah this this is all extremely up in
the air
um even within uh classic uh you know
sort of buddhist studies
and pedantic studies i'm and i'm not
you know i i don't want to try to get i
can't do an exhaustive thing of all of
these
so what i want to do is instead look at
the current the sort of the best
to my mind the best um overall take of
the debate
as it has found itself into uh modern
cognitive science because that's where i
know how to play the game
uh well and so that's how i'm going to
try and respond to this question
as as deeply as i can awesome thank you
thank you hey
rob g you have a question
rob g just pop off and
oh yes he's back yes yeah welcome okay i
hit the wrong button
there's too many buttons on this thing
um yeah my question john um
kind of leads to some of the earlier uh
points that that um
um strong was making uh so i'm just
gonna say uh what was the
maybe what's a problem when you're
meeting making your sense making
and using kind of an information
processing model
uh or a narrative model versus what
you're talking about
and then also like how might one use
your model in a small world network
more than kind of the old-fashioned
regular network that we
grew up in it's good to talk to you rob
um yeah i believe i owe you some
uh uh emails too so i i they i have not
forgotten about them
so um i don't think you're busy at all
um so i mean what i mean so
4e cognitive science is basically all
around the way in which
uh the so the standard way of
understanding information processing
has been the computational model and
then that
and part of the what's going on is the
idea that that
that smuggles in an entire cartesian
framework
and then sort of for heideggerian and
vickensteinian reasons and beyond that
that has all come into question and then
the what's what's replacing it is a
dynamical systems
model now the interesting thing is
um one of the things that alicia gerardo
and she's
uh the dynamics in action is the book on
that that how you sort of shift um
into uh using dynamical systems theories
to understand
cognition she did explicitly though in
that
book and i i mentioned this um
she did argue that narrative
was actually very important um and we
were we had we
we missed its functionality from the
standard information processing
precisely and this was really
interesting because
her argument was not the content of
narrative she was arguing that what
narrative does is
actually instantiate a like a dynamical
system style of processing
in our our cognition that part of our
cognition
of which we can be sort of self-aware
because what narrative does
is it gets you tracking multiple
variables
in a self-organizing fashion you have
the you have the foreshadowing the
feedback the layering
um the sensitive dependence on changes
in initial conditions
you have characters which are soft so
she gives this whole
very powerful argument uh that why
narrative is so important to us but
what's interesting is it's totally
different than the literary style
analysis of
of of narrative because she was
emphasizing
not any of the content she was
but the basically the pattern i guess
the way of putting it we
you actually instantiate uh a kind of
cognition
that enables you to better track
dynamical systems
and i think that actually is a more
powerful way
of talking about kudos narrative
practice hypothesis
hudo made it sort of very formulaic um
although he
he later on also comes to reject content
models he does that in the
in the work with with maya so i think if
we
what i what i really liked was strong
was was was the shift to that
to right trying to get a focus
on what do i want to say
you sort of the the phenomenology and
functionality that is
being instantiated in us in narrative
rather than
the actual content of the narrative and
so this is like what you're doing in
lexio
and this is like what you're doing in
circling where you're moving
off of the content of what you're
speaking and the speech is now more
directed
uh towards you know enabling uh the
the dynamical system to get into a flow
state
within distributed cognition that's how
i see this
i mean that that we would start to
uh we would start to treat narrative as
something that is much more
about instantiating
that right that that flow in distributed
cognition
uh that gives us you know it gives us a
transformative space
uh rather than just a space in which
um we might be reconceptualizing or even
rethinking about how we solve problems
which is what
sort of standard narrative practice does
so the model i'm having in mind when i'm
answering you rob is when i talked about
this you know um
you know when people are doing jeep form
and they're sort of enacting
drama and they're trying to deliberately
bleed between
enact it's like active role playing
believe between enacting the drama
and the patterns and right within their
within their so-called real lives the
explicit intent of that kind of
narrative drama
is to bleed right between right what's
happening within the drama
and what's happening in their lives and
so i see that as a very
a very important form of ritualized
serious play
that is designed to shift the intro
shift the focus
on to the instantiation of
a dynamical system rather than onto the
particular
content that we normally focus on when
we're doing narrative
i hope that answers your question but
that's that's what i think
is important here sorry john can i just
say that's a follow-up real quick
pardon me sir route yeah
yes yes so so if in the kind of the old
network
i'm just trying to find good nodes and
absorb their information or i'm trying
to put out good information
like what would i do differently if i'm
in this more dialectic network or i
don't know
how to say it you've just done it you
you what you do is
like you look for the design principles
by which and the type of network that is
resulting
so the model there is that like like i
said this way i'm doing all this work
with dan chappie
you know the way the the scientists
keep reconfiguring their social
organization
in order to manage the rovers on mars
they've got this dynamic
they've got a deliberately dynamic ser
right
constantly restructuring small world
network organization
and so it's not just that they're
connecting to the right people they pay
a lot of attention
to the way in which they're connected
like they they're so there's an
awareness of
design on connection and the kind of
network
that is being engendered so you're not
just trying to connect to the right
people
you're really trying to connect in the
right way where that means according to
the right principles that will afford
this kind of instantiation reliable
instantiation
of a dynamically restructuring small
world network
sorry john i just wanted to quickly jump
in there because it
this thought just occurred to me it
sounds very much to me like you're
taking the
that you think that narrative is by
default horizontal and you're trying to
reappropriate it to make it address the
vertical
yes sound right yes that's right and and
that goes exactly to the answer to rob
because part of that verticality
is right is is not i'm not reducing it
to this drum but part of that
verticality
is some is is is a mental awareness
right
a sort of metacognitive awareness of the
functionality
that rather than it being transparent to
you
and so yeah so exactly it's like an
exception
yes exactly rob does that did that
answer your follow-up question
yeah this was great that gave me a lot
of very abstract things to think about
well yeah i get that but the point is um
you need to pair that very abstract with
the stuff i'm trying to exemplify when
i'm doing the deal logos with people
yeah i know that part makes sense
perfectly yeah
great that was a good uh thanks john i
think that was a good additional
follow-up point thank you
oh my pleasure
hey ben you have a question for john
hi john ben here uh i had a question
coming up today
in uh in relation to the lesson that you
gave
um i was wondering if you see a
legitimate continuity between uh
this epicurean idea of a joy of being
and the jhanas in
in buddhism yeah
i think so i uh i think
i mean they come from sort of a a a
different ontology
um and they belong to sort of different
pedagogical programs
but i think they they might be both
instantiating
that yeah the i forget the sanskrit term
that sense of bliss
right it's the bliss in being yeah right
trying to get
analogous but where i see a potential
pedagogical difference so while i agree
that there's
a convergence in that sense um
i i i see the epicurean practice
uh as a a more accessible in
in the issue in the sense that we've
been talking about here the scalability
that they're more off the street
accessible to people
it's a way of getting that that tasting
of of the bliss of being that doesn't
require
you know the the absorption and training
that the genos typically require people
it definitely seems to be the case that
the uh the epicurean practices occur
in the context of a householder life
rather than in a monastic setting
yeah yeah and and like i said one of
and well
i'm trying to and i think this is fair
to mcclellan because
uh i think this is directly his intent
but i'm trying to expand on that
by teaching um the epicurean practices
sort of extended epicureanism
that in a way that seeds uh
uh stoicism and seeds neoplatonism so
that
uh in one sense it'll be standalone
accessible this is my attempt to address
the scalability problem
so i'm trying to get both these things
that'll be stand-alone accessible
but it also will seed people so they can
go to these deeper levels
so i am hoping that there can be this uh
synthamata between the traditions and
understanding the joy of being in terms
of janna's and the john is in terms of
the joy of being and
um and also that continuity between the
shallow accessible and the
what's deep totally i mean that that's
the intent
i mean the intent of presenting i keep
using this metaphor because it
keeps coming to mind i i see the the
the eastern and western traditions like
the two fields of vision
and the point is to figure out how to
actually integrate them into a kind of
depth perception
um i don't know
how appropriate it would be to go into
specifics but uh
this is this is salient to me because
i've been uh studying and practicing the
genres
uh recently in uh in my meditations and
uh
it seems like there's a lot of uh
overlap in the material that uh that
many meditation teachers used
pedagogically to to instruct students on
these states and
um the kind of practices that are being
discussed in this
section of uh of the course um
these things about attending to the the
stable and subtle uh pleasures
inherent in um in states of mind and
body that are free from suffering and
and what not yep i think so i think so
the the i i would i would also hope that
ben that it would go the other way
so i was really impressed by some work
that that what would be britain's done
on
you know that these genres you know
you're aware of this you know this like
the the the schemas and taxonomies you
get from the east
there isn't one there's a whole bunch of
them and they right
right and some are five and some have 27
and like
like like and so and the problem is
sorry i mean this is a gentle criticism
but i've encountered it perhaps you have
too
you get you know you encounter
parochialism around this right
you encounter people that say well if
you don't do 27 you just don't get it
and it really disheartening to people
and
and i think willingly britain's point to
be well there's no there's no sort of
non-parochial justification for any one
of these schemas
right so if we could get a better
discussion going
east-west that might help to orient
people more towards
you know a convergent functionality
rather than a parochial commitment to
any particular taxonomy
yeah and something that uh that real
practice always seems to be pointing to
is
assessing things in terms of your own
experience and um
yeah getting out of uh yeah dogmatic
adherence to parochial views and
and whatnot well that's that's exactly
right so the the idea of trying to set
up sort of
you know a deal logos between these two
traditions
is my way of trying to and
that's that's in fact explicitly why i'm
teaching the true tradition
it's it's to give people a platform
that will afford what you just said
afford them actually
shifting uh towards that uh
trans-parochial kind of orientation
to the practice so it's
definitely uh something something very
salient to me
um because of my background and uh so
i'll be trying to work
on that and uh and with this community
as as we go on
excellent i mean one of the great things
um that makes me i'm sorry it's not
sorry don't take it that i'm saying that
my pleasure about things
matters or is normative but one of the
things that is pleasing me
is how so many people are being drawn to
this community
you know of really high caliber you know
and also
you know high caliber in many different
in many different dimensions and
nevertheless
ways that are in which they're
convergent with each other i think
that's very very powerful i think that's
really good
well thank you for your time and care
and uh
you know interfacing with this community
and answering this question and and all
of that
um there's just one thing this this
isn't very important but uh
just to clear this up um i'm i'm showing
up on the youtube
live stream says uh with this string of
consonants
adm zmf um yeah and yeah there's
there's multiple bands on on the stream
uh just for the sake of
um clearing up any identity confusions
so i know that you're the band attached
to that string
um yes okay yeah
just uh sorry about the uh
let's sooner now no i i don't actually i
i don't actually
uh people have all kinds of reasons by
which they manage
the presentation of their identity on
these public forums i don't challenge
that because i don't know what
particular circumstances are
thank you for answering my question
thank you babe
[Music]
mike mike g you're up next
hello john uh thank you as always for
all the work that you're doing and
you being a part of this discord group
um thanks mike thank you for thank you
it's always helpful to me to hear that
by the way
um yeah you you deserve it all the time
your
i think your work is constantly
deserving of praise
um so my question is i'm i'm actually
feeling honestly a little struggled
in even asking it um
and please please i i don't even know if
it should even be
bothered because it seems like it would
involve a
kind of much deeper discussion that i
don't want to take away from others and
asking their questions
um but the question is it's going to
sound probably relatively simple but
it's for a much broader
question going on in my head that i'm
curious about
and i don't know if it's going to go
there and i'm not meaning to force it or
anything like that
and like i said to take up anybody's
time um but basically the question is um
i'm i'm wondering if you could speak on
the current state of cognitive research
or
not even necessarily cognitive research
but just any kind of
consciousness research or neuro you know
anything to do with
consciousness the general frame of the
idea
and as it relates towards
evolution and how is it
is it appearing as though the research
is moving in a direction
of that there is
signs or there aren't as many signs
that we we are having this desire to
craft religion
and and particularly so my question is
is
wanting to point toward religious praxis
and the way that we we have this what is
appearing to me
and like i said i don't have the science
behind this at all but it appears to me
as being there's this innate desire
on on our part to craft religion
and praxis in particular and that if
if there isn't a particular framing in
which we are pointing this toward
in the case of like you know um
the mysterium in the sense of like any
type of religious tradition and it's
pointing in that direction of the
mysterium
that if that's not there
it still has this desire to flow itself
out into praxis
and we can see this in varieties of
instances in
the human frame in the last you know
certainly i
i'm seeing it in in your awakened from
the meaning crisis and and
martin luther it just seems to just be
constantly coming out
time and time and time again and so
that's the basis of my question
that's a great question and you're right
um um
i i like it it's a deep answer but uh
my answer to that is going to start
coming out next week or the week after
so i have
uh started recording uh an ongoing
dialogue series
uh with greg enriquez um called
uh untangling the world not the hard
problems of mind and meaning
they're exactly about what's the best
account of
uh of of consciousness and why
or should we do we need to bring in uh
because greg and i have written
some blogs together on this why do we
need to bring into
why do we need to bring into it um the
relationship to the problem of meaning
meaning meaning in life not semantic
meaning and so
we are doing that and so it's a sequence
of sort of hour and 15 minute
conversations between he and i genuine
dialogues
i come at it of course from sort of the
angle of
philosophy and kagsai
and while greg is very philosophically
literate he comes at it from his
uh as a psychologist and a
psychotherapist
um and so we are directly addressing
exactly what you're asking
um and we
like i said um we've recorded four
already and
that's only about uh we're only about a
third of the way through the argument
so i suspect it's going to be a a total
of uh of 12
uh video uh recordings of greg and i
exploring exactly these connections that
you're pointing to
so yes very much so
and what what we're both trying to do
with our
uh with our respective uh expertise is
to bring together and condense as much
of the current uh cognitive science and
psychology and neuroscience etc but also
people talking about transformations of
consciousness and transformations of
self-consciousness that's the overlap
with
therapy and and mystical experiences
which
we're trying to bring all of that
together and put it into an integrated
presentation
and like i said we've we've recorded
four of those
i'm just working with ammar uh to get
some of the editing
and uh and a few of the the
the the window dressing up and then
we're gonna start releasing them like
next week
so i'm gonna i'm gonna i'm gonna try and
give you
basically a 12-hour answer to that
question
okay um i guess a follow-up question to
that i'm curious if
if you have any plans within this
space to speak directly with anybody
from within
a religious studies background
you know somebody's focusing
specifically on
a large broad general understanding of
religious studies as opposed to like a
specific
studies area i'm talking to one person
who's emeritus from that i've mentioned
i'm going to be and i've mentioned him
already because
uh i think one of the most important
books from somebody he's emeritus
religious studies
in the last 15 years is james carson's
uh the religious case against belief and
then his follow-up book
infinite games and we are recording a
deal logos together
on peter lindberg's stoa towards the end
of this month so that's coming down the
pipe
fantastic excellent thank you so much
john
thank you and i should just say on on
the subject of
simple questions not that i think that
that was all that simple question
i i want to encourage people to ask
simple questions you don't have to just
think of the deepest question possible i
know a lot of people
like to do that and we love those
questions but if you have just a simple
question about
a concept you didn't understand from say
awakening from the meaning crisis or
just
want to clarify something we want those
questions just as much as
the more detailed ones as well can i
follow up or
brat and i just can't conscious of what
happened
i want to recognize what happened
between manuel and i i
i might also get the question type wrong
uh you know because where we we just
have voice and we we're
we're you know we're just meeting and so
if i if i'm getting the type of question
you're answering
wrong please let me know uh i won't be
offended or anything i want to know i
want to i want to make sure
that i'm answering the question as it's
intended
as it's intended that i'm not i'm not
categorizing it the wrong way
or putting it at the wrong level of
response so
i i encourage people to make sure that i
know
uh that that that sorry no i know that's
too strong
that i have i have grasped uh the sort
of the intent
of the type of question and the level at
which people want it addressed
i want to be responsive i want to i i
mean i i
aspire to exemplify socrates's capacity
to like really adjust and fit his
answer to where the interlocutor is
speaking from
excellence mark you have a question
hello john of course i have a question
um i've i've been you know we had peter
lindbergh here and he was talking about
the mean plex
which is a term i despise um
and so we actually we we renamed it
because we can do that
um and and so like one of his concerns
is that
you know sort of like when you're out in
the meanplex it's too easy
for your message to get either lost or
manipulated or
something like that um and then so
i i like i said we we sort of have this
reformulation of the memplex
uh that were that were um
you know that basically we're using to
out compete memes
in some sense right and we're calling it
the realm of transformative coupling
and imagining is something like
well memes are these very low-res icons
attachments or something that aren't
really symbols they aren't really
metaphors
they aren't really parables and so i i
was
i was wondering if if there's something
in that space
and this is sort of to manuel's point i
guess in some way right
where where you know the available
cogsi and and you know all of the
available knowledge you bring to bear on
on
in terms of ecology of practices if
there's a an easy way
sort of into that space of
transformative coupling
you know through symbols or like maybe
what the history tells us about symbols
that are accessible to people and how we
involve them and therefore compete in
the mean plex
as it were with better with better tools
and what your thoughts were around that
so yeah i think that's an excellent
question and i don't
have the relative expertise in that but
i
i had i was fortunate um and i did uh
mention it to you guys what what needs
to be created are
are basically new genres uh
and so i i this is not meant to be
exhaustive mark it's meant to be
exemplary
i i i think what akira the dawn did
uh with the meaning wave i i think this
is a powerful way
uh because beca right because he's he's
breaking genres
he's creating a new genre he's creating
something that looks like a meme
or it looks like a jingle but it's
actually not right
it's designed to basically draw people
in and draw them into a deeper
conversation it's
not so what it's like it's like the way
a parable
undermines standard narrative it looks
like a meme and it draws people in but
it's actually designed to
to my mind and this is what i came
across in the discussion with him
it's actually designed to uh undermine
the stance that people take when they're
consuming memes
and actually draw them into a deeper
engagement i like what you called it
right what did you call it some kind of
coupling what was the name again
the realm of transformative coupling
transformative coupling and so what he's
trying to do with the
with the with the meaning wave right is
to create
something that's seductive in the sense
that it looks like a meme
or it's like or like it's seductive like
a parable
it looks like a meme it draws you in and
then it explodes the very
consumerist um you know uh superficial
salience attitude
that drives the mean plex and and
undermines it by getting people
it basically ushers them into um
that kind of transformative coupling i
don't have the skill to do that
um that i i just i don't but why
i wanted why i was so interested in
what he was doing and talking to him is
because
like again i'm not saying that that's
again i want to repeat
it's not exhaustive but it's exemplary
of the kind of thing that is needed
that's exactly the kind of thing that is
needed i can't generate that
i don't have the skills i don't have the
expertise but people who do
like him i think need to generate things
of that ilk
yeah that's that yeah we're certainly on
the same page on that so i guess
i guess as a hopefully quick follow-up
although probably not um
i i'm you know i i hear you talking
about uh
uh stealing the culture and uh right
so what what happened say during the
last time the culture got stolen
you know that that that we can look at
perhaps
um you know to to to utilize i mean i
know one thing that uh
somebody who comes on here occasionally
mentioned was um
uh uh the whole idea behind
the french revolution was sort of
spawned off by art for example
right so that that sort of you know any
any handles
uh that we have into that and then yeah
hopefully we'll get the artists right or
we have availability to the artists to
do the work once with it once we can
schematize it for them to some extent
right and then what was also needed
what's also needed
um so the example that comes to mind is
you know the one that i tend to use is
um
you know how christianity stole the
culture of the roman empire
and you have you you have to well part
of what the answer is
exactly what's happening here uh you
have to build
communities but you also have to network
communities together
um that's why the thing that rafe kelly
did a couple weeks ago the movement
summit
where you have all these emerging uh uh
communities of practice
and and and their attendant research and
they all
we were getting together and and there
was this very rich exchange
and it wasn't any attempt to you know
nobody was saying
my way is the way or my community is the
community
it was this attitude of no let's all
find a way
to network together because that's
what's actually happening
right you've got what the christians did
was they you know they set up all these
uh churches but they also had mechanisms
informal mechanisms almost shamanistic
mechanisms
where people are constantly moving
between the churches either literally by
journeying
or by letters and what you have for a
very long time is you don't have
you don't have the hierarchical
structure that became the catholic
church
you had instead this this this co-op
that was constantly redesigning and
redefining itself
and i i think that's also something we
like it's not just a matter of how we
present the material
it's also important to think about how
we grow
the culture how we like how how we and i
mean literally
how do we afford what i was talking to
rob about
you know how do we afford the formation
of
of dynamically continually redestruct
restructuring and redefining
small world network of these emerging
communities of practice i think this is
a very
important problem and again this is part
of why i'm talking to jordan hall so
much i don't have the relevant expertise
for that
uh uh but i'm trying to find the people
who do
and that's also why i'm doing all that
work with dan shapi about the scientists
on how they move the rovers around
because i want to understand
possible ways in which human beings can
make these kinds of dynamical
uh small world networks in uh
the social organization of distributed
cognition so that we can better afford
this
the like we have to internet
people together if we're gonna commit
and we're gonna compete
with the way the you know the the the
the the mindless and impersonal aspects
of the internet you know create the meme
plex
we have to have something that competes
with it
um uh in in in in real time
yeah yeah i thought i thought that was
something like what your answer would be
so yeah i think we're going to go after
the art
next right that's probably our next big
big push thank you john i i appreciate
that
that's good feedback okay well thank you
very much guys i i
i appreciate it and uh thank you uh
for that follow these questions mark
because um like i said i think they you
indicated that it might also give
a more uh uh cogent response uh to
manuel which
i'm happy about so thank you for that
do you have time for two more john um i
have time for one more how's that
all right uh veloskin you've got you've
got the last question
hi john um so we
the the root now discretion here kind of
ground to a halt a little bit
and then we had a little discussion and
um
we decided that we had to formulate the
problem and work out the
uh what's it the
the functionality of religion in order
to
address the problem properly so we're
doing that we've had to read up
the like the topics
to address and mine is the perennial
problems
so i thought i would ask you to help me
cheat on my homework
and tell me what your what your concept
of
the perennial problems are like maybe a
short list or something
well i could do something better i can
email to brett a document that
christopher and i have written
that tries to lay out um
as in sync and comprehensive fashion as
we can
a a principle taxonomy of the perennial
problems i could email that and he could
make that available to you guys
would that be helpful that's perfect
thank you very much
yeah so yeah but take it with the right
way
again none of this is meant to be
exhaustive or complete
i'm hoping it will be helpful
scaffolding for you guys
yeah very helpful so yeah brett let's
make sure that
um can i ask you to make sure that i do
this
absolutely i'm giving you free
permission to
harass me until i make sure that i get
that document to you
because i do want to help help that way
definitely i'll follow up uh with that
and thanks thank you so much john
uh for coming out again now so this was
a makeup week because a lot because we
missed last week
and you've been kind enough to let us
get back on track so you will actually
be back
next week that's exactly right brett i
will be here next week
uh to again uh every time i do this i
find the caliber of questions
uh i i find it it's getting uh they're
getting just progressively better and
better
um and and they were very good to begin
with so i'm very happy i'm very happy to
be here again next week i'm looking
forward to it
thank you so much but again just a
reminder they don't have to be the great
deep questions
exact questions are great too exactly
so let's all work to help each other
address the scalability issue
however there's no shame in one-upping
yourself
that's right yeah yeah well both both
directions
uh are are welcomed both directions are
welcome
so thank you very much yeah thank you
again john thanks straw and everyone
else who asked questions tonight thank
you manuel for recording
and again we'll be back uh next week uh
so so stay tuned thanks everyone
thank you john